# Mohammad Merajul Islam Molla Toronto, Canada

Email: meraj.enigma@gmail.com • Mobile: + (1) 647-261-4628 • Skype: mmm2177

LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/merajenigma

Github: imeraj

Medium: https://medium.com/@merajulislam

## Summary

About 11 years of industry and academic experience work- Have experience working in multiple countries - USA, Japan, ing with diverse technologies ranging from low-level system software to mobile/web applications, project management, company strategy & policy making, along with new business development and introducing new technologies to meet dynamic nature of tech industry.

India, South Korea and with clients from different countries -USA, South Korea, Japan, and Australia. Good verbal and written communication skills and comfortable working with colleagues and clients from diverse cultures.

INTERESTS: New Technology R&D, Software Architecture, Project Management, Mobile Application Development, Server-side Programming, Software Quality Assurance, Embedded Systems, Recruitment & Team Building

## Experience

## Application Architect (Web Technology), Rakuten Inc, Tokyo, Japan

Jun 2018 - Oct 2019

- Worked as Technical Leader of Event Management Platform (EMP) Web Application (Spring Boot, Angular Js, jBPM, Batch, etc).
- Designed architecture of EMP based on Microservices (Spring Cloud, Spring Cloud Stream, Spring Cloud Contracts) and improved current monolith architecture.
- Interviewed candidates, built teams, and trained members.

### CTO (Mobile Technology), Monstar Lab Bangladesh, Dhaka, BD

*Jan 2017 - Oct 2017* 

- Supervised Mobile (iOS, Android), Infrastructure, and QA Teams.
- Supervised projects: Earthcar (http://www.earthcar.co.jp) Taxi app (Android) Uber like taxi booking app. Conducted R&D for iOS app.
- Conducted regular trainings, tech talks, and internal tech sessions for high performance team building.
- Was highly involved in recruitment, project estimation, employee evaluation, and company strategy determination.

#### Senior Architect (Mobile Technology), Monstar Lab Bangladesh, Dhaka, BD May 2016 - Dec 2016

- Built and supervised Mobile (iOS, Android) teams from scratch.
- Worked as Tech Lead and Project Manager for mobile projects (iOS, Android).
- Supervised projects: A2MILKBAR departmental store management app (iOS, Android, PHP/Node.js), Askul (http://www.askul.co.jp) - E-commerce App (iOS, Android).

#### Chief Engineer (Mobile SW), Samsung R&D Institute Bangladesh, Dhaka, BD Mar 2014 - May 2016

- Worked as Tech Lead of Samsung Gear S and Gear Fit Manager applications and managed 20+ team members.
- Supervised multiple internal projects for iOS, Android and Tizen platforms Log Analyzer, Emergency Service, TizenFlip, Samsung Guardian App, etc.
- Managed small team of 3 members to contribution to open source project Linaro.

#### Lead Engineer (Mobile SW), Samsung R&D Institute Bangladesh, Dhaka, BD May 2012 - Mar 2014

- Worked as Team Lead of Call and Driver Teams of Feature Phone Mobile Commercialization division and managed around 10+ team members.
- Worked as Tech Lead of Qshare (Quick Share) project on Android platform.

#### System SW Engineer (MAC OS Graphics Driver Team, NVIDIA, CA, USA

*Jan 2008 - Aug 2011* 

- Worked on various components of Display Drivers and core RM Software (Hotplug Architecture, Display Port, Mobile PCI Express Module (MXM), Interrupt Handling, DVI Port, HDCP Protocol, VBIOS, etc).
- Implemented in C and x86 assembly.

## MTS Intern (CPD, VMware ESX Server Team), VMware, CA, USA

*May* 2007 - *Aug* 2007

- Developed Kernel Crash Dump tool for VMware ESX Server.
- Implemented in C and bash script.

- Developed Filesystem Debugger for VMware ESX Server.
- Implemented in C and bash script

### **Education**

## Marquette University, MS in Computing

Dec 2007

• CGPA: 4.00/4.00

• Final Project: Implementation of device driver for Broadcom's BCM4713 Ethernet card on Linksys WRT54GL router and integrating it with Xinu Kernel.

BUET, BS in CSE Nov 2004

• CGPA: 3.92/4.00

• Thesis: Study of Various Popular Network Simulators and Case Studies using NS-2, Commonly Used Open Source Network Research Simulator, to Simulate Wired and Wireless Networks.

#### **Technical Skills**

**Programming Languages:** Swift • Elixir • Go • Java • Kotlin • Ruby • Objective-C • C • C++ • Assembly(x86, MIPS)

Mobile Platforms: iOS • Android

Mobile Architecture Patterns: MVC • MVP • VIP • RxVIP

Mobile Frameworks/Tools: RxSwift • ReSwift • RxJava • Reductor • Alamofire • Retrofit 2 • Glide • Picasso • AlamofireImage • KingFisher • Firebase • Dagger 2 • ARKit • CoreML • Google Analytics

Web Frameworks (Backend): Phoenix • Ruby on Rails • Spring Boot • Spring Cloud • Gorilla (golang)

Web Frameworks (Frontend): React • Angular • Phoenix LiveView

**APM Tools:** Prometheus • Scout • AppSignal • New Relic

Quality Assurance: Cucumber • Calabash • XCTest • ExUnit • MiniTest

Infrastructure: Docker • Kubernetes

Database: Mysql • Sqlite • Realm • MongoDB • Redis • Elastic Search

**Project Management:** JIRA • Redmine • Trello **Version Control:** Git • Perforce • Subversion

Real-time Services: Pusher • PubNub

Miscelleneous: GraphQL • Protobuf • RabbitMQ • Kafka • Apache JackRabbit • Big Data (Apache Hadoop, MapReduce, Sqoop, Hive, HBase) • Machine Learning (Scikit-learn, NumPy, Pandas) • Deep Learning (Keras)

### **Past Professional Projects**

## Earthcar Taxi App (iOS, Android)

2017

Uber like Taxi app for Earthcar (http://www.earthcar.co.jp) Japan. Three different applications - User App (Android, Smartphone), User App (iOS, Smartphone) and Driver App (Android, Tab) along with backend APIs/services and front-end Admin panel.

- Worked as Tech Lead and Project Manager for mobile apps.
- Conducted R&D, designed app architecture, and guided engineers to implement features.
- Derived project estimation from client requirements, broke down features into sprints, worked with QA Engineers to define test specifications.
- Conducted code review and managed branch/release policies.
- Collaborated with backend engineers for smooth integration of APIs/services with mobile apps.

### Askul E-commerce App (iOS, Android)

2017

E-commerce applications developed for Askul (http://www.askul.co.jp) Japan. Two different applications - one for iOS and another for Android

- Worked as Tech Lead and Project Manager for the project.
- Conducted R&D, designed app architecture, and guided developers to implement features.
- Conducted code review and managed branch/release policies.
- Backend APIs/services developed using Java (Spring Boot) by 3rd party in Japan.
- Conducted regular meeting and status reporting with Japan side project stakeholders.

Departmental store management app developed for Australian client. Two different applications - one for iOS and another for Android platform along with backend APIs/services and front-end Admin panel.

- Worked as Tech Lead and Project Manager for the project.
- Conducted R&D, designed app architecture, and guided developers to implement features.
- Conducted code review and managed branch/release policies.
- Supervised backend APIs/services development using PHP and Node.js.

## Samsung Gear S and Samsung Gear Fit Apps (iOS)

2015-2016

Developed commercial versions of Samsung Gear S and Gear Fit Apps to work with Tizen powered Gear S2 and Gear Fit 2.

- Developed in collaboration with Samsung HQ (South Korea).
- Conducted R&D, designed and developed Basic Accessory Protocol (BAP) on top of Bluetooth Low Energy (BLE). The protocol supports file transfer with pause/resume/cancel, CRC and re-transmission, QoS
- Designed and developed Webproxy module to support multiple Gear apps, such as Weather, S-Voice, Voice Memo, etc.
- Notifications using Apple Notification Center Service, along with notification settings, block notifications.
- Samsung Gear S https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/samsung-gear-s/id1117310635?mt=8
- Samsung Gear Fit https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/samsung-gear-fit/id1117312500?mt=8

## **Open Source Contribution**

### Linaro Project - http://www.linaro.org

2015

Led team of 3 engineers for making contribution to Open Source project (Linaro) - open source software for ARM SoCs and made decent contribution to their power management tools - powertop, powerdebug, idlestat, and pm-qa.

### Xinu Project - https://github.com/xinu-os/xinu

2006-2007

Made significant contribution to MIPS port of Xinu kernel - exception and interrupt handler, timer, ethernet driver, etc.

## **Technical Articles**

My technical articles, specially on Elixir/Phoenix and Machine Learning can be viewed and read at https://medium.com/@merajulislam

#### Achievement/Awards

- 2017 Ranked 2nd in Monstar Lab ISUCON Tech Olympics (Web App Performance Tuning contest)
- 2017 Promoted as CTO of Mobile Technology Division
- 2015 Won Employee of the Year Award (SRBD)
- 2015 Won Iconic Team award for iOS Gear Manager Team for 2H of Y2015 (SRBD)
- 2014 Nominated as Employee of the Year (SRBD)
- 2014 Iconic Team award for Android Development Team for 2H of Y2014 (SRBD)
- 2013 Achieved Double promotion (promoted from Lead Engineer to Chief Engineer, SRBD)
- 2006-2007 Won Graduate Assistantship (Marquette University)
- 1999-2003 Won Dean's List Award (BUET)
- 1999-2003 Won University Merit Scholarship (BUET)
- 1996-2003 Won Board Merit Scholarship (Bangladesh Government)